גוט טוב G'tov everybody, today's דף Daf is צ"ג Tzadik Gimmel and
as I indicated, it's going to be a quite an interesting one.
We pick up with the משנה Mishna and we're dealing of course
with issues about people coming with different claims and how the money
is divided in terms of the כתובה, Kesuvah,
and the first issue was about the whole כתובת בנין דכרין, Kesubas
Benin Dichrin, right? And when are the heirs entitled to take away
their what their mothers had brought into the estate before the normal
division. Now we get to an issue about competing claims. Let's take
a look. מי שנשא שלוש נשים, Mi she'nasah shalosh nashim, a man
was married to three women, ומת, Umet, and he died. וכתובתה של
זו מנה ושל זו מאתיים ושל זו שלוש מאות. V'kesuvatah shel zu
maneh v'shel zu masayim v'shel zu shalosh meos. And רש"י Rashi says
that we are talking that they all were married on the same
day, okay? It was a special, who was that? Reverend Sun Myung
Moon. Oh, that was only to get a hundred people, but they
reached men and women pairs, okay? Here, the guy set up with
three brides under the חופה, Chuppah, okay? And maybe if we want
to really make it perfect, the two of them made the third
one a שליח, Shaliach, so he gave the money to one woman
and was married to all three of them and it didn't have
to be that, but okay, they were all married on the same
day because if they were married on different days, then the one
with the prior כתובה Kesuvah has the prior liens and it really
doesn't matter the amount of money, okay? That, so the earlier the
person with the earlier liens collects and whatever is left over, you
know, the next people get and we actually had that, right, a
little bit yesterday as well, right? Same day, not time of day.
Well, the גמרא's Gemara going to get to, the משנה Mishna will
get to a question of the time of the day, whether it
was that precise, but okay. So we're talking that they were all
married on the same day, okay.
ומת, Umet, and he died. וכתובתה של זו מנה ושל זו מאתיים
ושל זו שלוש מאות. V'kesuvatah shel zu maneh v'shel zu masayim v'shel
zu shalosh meos. And one had a כתובה Kesuvah of a hundred,
one had two hundred, one had three hundred. ואין שם אלא מנה,
V'ein sham ela maneh, and the estate is only worth a hundred.
How do they divide it? They each have equal claims. חולקות בשווה,
Cholkos bishaveh, they divide it equally. All right, now why you should
say one has a larger claim, but the way the logic is
on that first hundred they all have equal claims. They all want
the full amount of that first hundred, so their claims are all
equal, they divide it equally.
All right, that's fine. היו שם מאתיים, Hayu sham masayim,
there was two hundred. של מנה נוטלת חמישים, Shel maneh nosnes chamishim,
the one whose claim is a hundred gets fifty. של מאתיים ושל
שלוש מאות שלושה שלושה של זהב, Shel masayim v'shel shalosh meos shlosha
shlosha shel zahav,
three golden coins, the golden coin is twenty-five, so it's seventy-five. So
if we draw it like this,
okay I actually wanted to keep this up here for my שיעור,
Shiur, but we'll draw it over here. Okay if we draw it,
so you've
got, so you've got a hundred, two hundred, three hundred. That's the
size of their כתובה. Kesuvah.
Okay and here's the size of the estate.
And the size of the estate is, so if it's a hundred,
then it is thirty-three and a third, thirty-three and a third, thirty-three
and a third.
Fine.
So that's if it's a hundred. That, okay, which makes sense because
they all have equal claims on the hundred. If it's two hundred,
the משנה Mishna says what do you do? Fifty, seventy-five, seventy-five. Now
if you think about it, that makes no sense. And the גמרא's
Gemara going to say it makes no sense. Why does it make
no sense? It doesn't seem to follow this rule. Why don't they
each get half? Because, well, no, but it doesn't make sense they
all divide, well yes you could say they all get a third,
they all get sixty-six and two thirds, end of story, because in
the end nobody's going to collect more than they're owed, so since
they all maybe you keep on dividing it until people are paid
out, okay? But the way the logic seems to be that we
actually look at the amounts that they have equal claims on. On
the first hundred they all have equal claims, right? They all say
that first hundred goes to me. So in that hundred it's divided
equally, okay?
This is how you should be, logically you should be doing it,
which is what they did initially. Now on the next hundred, so
this is one hundred, two hundred, and three hundred all have equal
claims. But on the next hundred, the hundred guy falls off. Their
entire claim was as it were, you know, the first hundred. That's
the conceptual model here, okay? So on the next hundred, the two
hundred and the three hundred are the only ones who have claims,
but they all have equal claims because this two hundred guy says
two hundred was owed to me and the three hundred guy three
hundred was owed me, your guy, it's women, see that just shows
the whole male bias, we're talking about women and I'm still saying
guy. Okay, so this anyway, so this one they actually should divide
equally, right? So that should be fifty, fifty. Okay, then that's a
hundred, two hundred. So that's how it should be, so it should
be thirty-three, eighty-three and a third, eighty-three and a third. Fifty, seventy-five,
seventy-five does not make sense, does not follow that model. They all
have the same equal claims to the hundred, so they get fifty,
fifty, and fifty and then the נותר Notar they get the divide
that another twenty-five and twenty-five. Wait, wait, what are you saying?
Fifty, fifty, fifty. I said. In other words, everyone's got equal claim
to the hundred, so when it's 200- Yeah. Everyone gets 50- Wait,
what do you mean everyone gets 50? There's only 100, you can't
divide 100 into three sections of 50. No, no, no, for 200,
you equalize the 50, 50, 50 and then- Why do you equalize
50, 50, 50? Why don't you equalize 66, 66,
66? Why don't you equalize 40, 40, 40?
No, no,
no, what they're saying is you go- why? So the first one
is a third, a third, a third. Yes. Then you bump up
for 200, everyone gets 50- So my question is why do you
bump it up only to 50? That's arbitrary.
You would have been just as happy if I would have said,
you know, 60, 70, 70. You bump everybody up to 60 and
then you divide the rest. Why do you decide 50 as your
arbitrary level to bump them up? Okay,
fine. So that doesn't make sense. This is going to make- okay,
let's look at- the גמרא Gemara is going to have a very
arbitrary explanation in order to explain that, okay? Let's take a look.
וכן בבעלי חוב. v'chein b'baalei chov. Yeah, it would be the same
with בעלי חוב. baalei chov. Let's read the next case. Okay, let's
read the next case.
Okay, so היתה שם שלוש מאות- hayta sham shalosh me'ot 300- was
the estate. שמנה נוטלת חמישים, shemane notela chamishim, שמאתיים מנה, she'matayim mane,
ושלש מאות שישה של זהב, v'shalosh me'ot shisha shel zahav, which is
6 times 25- 150. Okay,
so if there was 300, it says- what does
it say? Let me find a better סיפא. seifa.
I'm sorry, yes. If it was 300, שהשלש מאות- she'shalosh me'ot היתה
שם שלוש מאות, hayta sham shalosh me'ot, שמנה נוטלת חמישים. shemane notela
chamishim.
So this poor guy gets only still 50. He gets- woman, thank
you. My God, I am so- that really- gosh, I should get
fired right now. Okay, so what's that about? Right? Now here
actually, it actually makes sense based on a different model. And here's
the different
model: 300, 200, 100. If you think about that, if you think
about their proportional claims, not about 'I get, we all claim'- this
is
one-sixth, two-sixths, three-sixths, right? If you think about that, right? Everybody understand
that point? Yes. So if you think about that, that as if
they have a proportional
claim. Okay, so one-sixth of 300 is
50. Two-sixths of 300 is 100. Three-sixths of 300- a half- is
150. So this model actually works well based on their proportional claim,
okay? That does not explain this model, okay? Or this model, right?
Because if you applied that to this model, then it would be
one-sixth, it'd be 16, right? It would be 33 and a third
and it would be 50. So this is a very nice model
for down here, does not explain either of these. Okay, this model
is you divide the amount in dispute and who the heck knows
what this model- feels like three unrelated models and this one we
don't even know what the principle is. All right, let's read the
last line of the משנה mishna and then I am going to
tell you the what Robert Aumann said
as he solved the riddle of the משנה. mishna. I also found
the English version of- Yes, well that's his English- online? Yeah, online
there's a PDF online. Did you send that to me? Okay, I
couldn't find that. Okay, I didn't want to have to buy the
book. Okay, it says וכן ג' שהטילו לכיס. v'chein gimel she'hitilu lakis.
Now here, relating to the last case, the משנה mishna says (this
is how תוספות Tosafot understands it), we're talking about the last case,
we're saying the same would be true if three different people made
an investment, הטילו לכיס. hitilu lakis. They all went into business together.
You contributed 100, I contributed 200, Michael contributed 300, and we all
went ahead and we made an investment. And then we earn money
off the investment. How should we divide the profit? Well, we should
divide the profit based on proportionally how much we contributed to the
investment, right? You get the amount of shares as it were equal
to the amount of money, proportional money you invested. So that works
for the last case. פיחתו או הותירו כך הן חולקין. pichatu o
hotiru kach hen cholkin. If we- if the investment made money or
lost money, we divide it based on our proportional investment. So the
last thing makes sense, and it makes sense to apply that to
an investment. It is not the model for these two. So comes
along Professor Robert Aumann, right? From- economist, mathematician, game theory. It's
in his book? The collected papers of Robert Aumann. Okay, and he
basically has one in here which says something about- he's got a
paper, where's his paper? Anyway, it's about the three women. Game theory
volume 36. There you go.
Anyway,
I'm trying to look for the one that it's about the- about
the story about the women, but he's got it in Hebrew, it
was printed in the journal מוריה Moriah as well, which is a
Hebrew Torah journal. So it was a great זכות, zechut, you know?
He- this is פשט pshat in the משנה! mishna! So you need
a little game theory to explain פשט pshat in משנה, mishna, and
here was his... Here is how he explained it, and once you
hear this you'll say, oh, that's gotta be the פשט. pshat. So
he points out that already רש״י, Rashi, and actually already the גאונים,
Geonim, said that this is based on the model of you focus
on the part that's in dispute and that's what you sort of
debate equally the part as opposed to the part that's, I mean
divide equally as opposed to the part that's conceded that's already conceded
by one of the sides. So for example it's basically the principle
of the first משנה mishnah בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia. First משנה mishnah
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia says we're both holding onto a טלית, tallis,
right? And I say it's all mine and Michael says it's all
his, we divide it equally. Let's say I say it's half mine,
we picked it up at the same time, and Michael says, you
know, I'm thinking I'm being a real צדיק, tzaddik, I'm admitting we
picked it up at the same time and Michael of course says,
not being the צדיק, tzaddik, sorry, you know you don't get away
in business by being a צדיק, tzaddik, you don't get ahead by
being a צדיק. tzaddik. Michael says what are you talking about? I
picked it up first, it's all mine. How do we divide it?
Okay, so you could say maybe one third, two thirds, you could
still say maybe it's still half and half. What the משנה mishnah
says is, is that I have implicitly conceded half to Michael. So
he walks away with half to begin with. What we're really just
debating is the remaining half and that we divide equally. So I
get a quarter, you get three quarters. Okay, which is sort of
like I said, you know, that that I was trying to apply
here, but it didn't work. Let's focus on the part that each
side is sort of conceded, right, and then we're debating the first
hundred equally, the other stuff, you know, the first guy's, the first
woman is saying I'm not having a claim on those so then
you proceed except then it should have led to a different division,
and that's going to be the problem to solve. But the first
thing is, you know, already the גאונים Geonim and רש״י Rashi already
have said that that is the principle that's sort of should be
operative here, okay, that we focus on what's conceded and we divide
equally the part that's not. Here was his insight to solve the
problem: We focus on every collection of three people or could be
a hundred people, doesn't matter, but what we're going to do is
it has to, we're going to find the problem that would work
for any two of them or for every single pairs of twos,
which means the following, let me
sort of show it out. Let's do this one which is the
hardest one. He says let's take a look at, let's assume there
were just two people. Let's take a look at based on the
solution, we're going to work backwards from the solution we've presented, okay?
This doesn't tell you how to get to the solution but shows
you what the solution is. Okay, we've divided 50 and 75 between
the 100 and 200, right? Okay, so 50 and 75 the total
is how much? 125.
Let's say you had a case of 100 and 200 and they
were debating 175.
With me? How would that work? So in the 100 they would,
so if you had 100 and 200 debating 125, here's what you
would say. On the first 100 of the 125, right? The first
100 of that they have equal claims. That we're going to divide
equally. The next 25 this guy isn't making any claim to, so
that we're just going to give all to the next guy. So
that's 50 and 75. That's exactly what we've got. Okay, let's say
now it was so
let's look at 200 and 300. The combined, the combined amount there
is 150, right? So let's say you had 150 that was being
disputed by 200 and 300. Is anybody conceding anything in that case?
No. So 75 and 75. And that's what you've got. Now even
if you did number three and number one, right? So let's is
anybody conceding anything? Because the 200 guy says I have a full
claim to the 150. That doesn't exceed my claim, I got a
full claim. Let's say you had 300 and 100, right? That's 125,
okay?
100 and 300, 125.
The first 100 they're disputing equally,
the next 25 he's not disputing, 50 and 75. So it worked
perfectly. Basically the way it works is you look at each pair,
right, and you find and the amount that's being divided by that
pair, right, works in terms of this principle of you give one
of the halves what he or she's what's being conceded and the
part that's not conceded you divide equally. Now that describes what we're
seeing, and you could go ahead, it works by all of this.
Okay, so why did the 100 and 300 that last one?
Because on the first 100 they're disputing it equally, right? They're disputing
the first so that's divide 50-50. Nobody's conceded. The last 25, right?
Okay. So now he says that describes the solution. It's almost like
a Sudoku thing, like you know there are rules that explain what
you have to fill in the box, but maybe in theory there
could be multiple things you could fill in the box that could
work. That doesn't tell you how to get to the solution. So
then he goes to prove that in any case of any amount
being disputed and of any number of claimants, there's always one and
exactly one unique solution that follows these rules. Which made it publishable
and then it and then it stayed. shows you how you get
to that solution. So this was just working backwards, okay? But what
he shows is that there is actually always one and uniquely one
solution no matter how many claimants and no matter how much the
money is. And if you go ahead and you work it, it
works by all of these, right? So in this case, right, although
it looked like this was 166 266, it really works on this
principle.
150 being disputed by 100 and 200, right? The first 50s are
divided, 50-50, and the last 50 isn't disputed, so it's 50 and
100, right? And let's say it was 250 being disputed by 200
and 300. So the first 200 is in dispute, right? If it's
250 being divided by 200 and 300, the first 200 is in
dispute, so that gets divided equally, right? The next 50 is not
in dispute, that goes all to the 300 guy, that's 100 and
150. So it actually works for every single row of this column,
you know, this idea. Now again, that doesn't tell me so how
you would figure it out. Actually it could be a fun game,
right? I could give you some scenarios and you could figure out,
you know, you could try to figure out what thing is going
to solve it. But basically it works based on the principle of
שנים אוחזין, Shnayim Ochzim, okay, with the fact that you always look
at any two at a time and it has to work for
all the groupings of twos that are there, that the amount you've
assigned those two people of your groupings follows these rules of שנים
אוחזין. Shnayim Ochzim. Oh my god, how long did it just take
me to explain that? We
could explain something like כל שנים, Kol Shnayim, yeah, whatever, 1800 years
for Dr. Robert Aumann to figure it out. First of all, why
did it take 1800 years to figure it out? Okay.
Now you all now you all know the משנה Mishnah that has
not been figured out for 1800 years since its writing. Now we're
going to look at the גמרא, Gemara, okay?
Take a look, you want to know what the ראשונים Rishonim say?
Take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. תוספות Tosafot says בכתובות שלוש מאות
דכתבות בעל שלוש מאות, Be-Kesubot shalosh me'ot de-ka-savos ba'al shalosh me'ot, that's
one of the answers of the גמרא. Gemara. This little תוספות... Tosafot...
לא ידע רבי מאי, lo yada Rebbi mai, no, not that's מאי
קא משמע לן, mai ka-mashma lan, that's a different point. דאמרה לה
מדין דאמאי דסליק, de-amra lah mi-din de-amai de-salik, you see that תוספות,
Tosafot, דאמרה לה, de-amra lah, לא אתפרש שפיר טעמא דהני מילתא. lo
Ispareish shappir ta'ama de-hainai milta. Who has
not been well explained what's going on here? All right, so anyway,
so nobody really knew, okay? Everybody came up with ad hoc explanations.
All right, let's take a look now at the... they didn't understand
it mathematically. Yeah, I mean, but you know, Michael is true like
if that it could have been said, a hint could have been
given like the כלל, Klal, כל שנים הם חולקין אותו, Kol Shnayim
hem cholkin oto, blah, blah, blah, you know, you know,
but it didn't. But anyway, so yeah, so the presumably that was
what was going on in the משנה. Mishnah. The interesting thing is
that explanation was lost and then they couldn't reconstruct it. Do you
think that they understood the economic basis of what they were... well,
no, there's not a... just because he's explained the rules doesn't mean
that it had to be those rules. You know, you could have
easily, he says at the beginning of his paper, you could have,
it's relatively arbitrary in these scenarios what rules you decide are going
to be applied. You could have said that you keep on dividing
everything equally until each claimant gets their full amount, right, which privileges
the guy who has the... the woman who has the smaller claim,
because you know, but okay.
Or you could have said, you know, you always divide it based
on proportion, like it looked like that was this rule. So it's
not like this is necessarily the fairest, it's a rule. Okay, but
the question is what is the rule? Okay, but then where does
it come from? The rules extrapolated from... right, this principle of שנים
אוחזין, Shnayim Ochzim, the logic behind it is the part you're conceding
should not be the part that's divided. But that doesn't have to
be the principle, you know. So right. But today do they understand
that that's what they were... well רש"י Rashi does, yeah, רש"י Rashi
does sort of bring in that idea, but he doesn't sort of
say you do it by looking at them in pairs of twos.
You look at them as a group of three and then it
doesn't work. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
של
מנה נוטלת חמישים. Shel Maneh noteles chamishim. So it says the מנה
Maneh gets... so now the גמרא Gemara is going to be bothered
with this, okay, because this is the one that you know, this
like I said, this follows a rule, this follows a rule, not
the same rule,
not
Robert Aumann's rule. This follows a rule, they don't follow the same,
but this doesn't seem to follow any rule. Okay, so this is
the one we really want to understand. So let's take a look.
של מנה נוטלת חמישים. Shel Maneh noteles chamishim. The woman with the
100 כתובה Ketubah gets
50. תלת ותלת ותילתא דאית לה. Talas ve-talas ve-tilsa d'is lah. It
should have been 33 and a third, right? Because we said if
you follow the logic of what's conceded, but you follow it as
a group of three, right? So in that case, right, 100, 200,
and 300,
where it's 200 here, so the first 100 that's equally debated, right?
And the next 100 is conceded here and here it's equally debated.
So following the idea that it goes by what's conceded, but looking
at them as a group
it should have been, right, this is should have been what it
should have been, right? And that's what the גמרא Gemara is assuming.
So you see the גמרא Gemara already assumes implicitly you go by
the idea of you only you divide equally you focus you concede
what's conceded and then you divide the rest equally. But if you
look at it as a group of three then that's how it
should be divided. Okay, and that's why it says why 50, it
should have been 33 and a third. One thing I didn't
understand, why the ask, what gave anyone the idea that you have
to look at it in terms of pairs? That I don't know,
but that seems to be the rule that explains the משנה. Mishna.
And how did what's-his-name,
Robert Aumann, how did he even... I don't know, that would be
a good question. You could sit down... I don't know.
What his mind worked that he figured that out you could look
at it in terms of two? Yeah, I don't know. We have
to remember he's been working on problems like this for roughly 30
years at the time he tackled this
problem. I understand. Alright, so can we go on? Okay, so מנה
מאתיים ושלש מאות Manah Matayim U'Shelosh Me'os plus וכולהו דאית ליה Vechulhu
De'is Leh should have been 33 and
a
third. אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel בכותבת בעלת מאתיים לבעלת מנה דין ודברים
אין לי עמך במנה. BeChoteves Ba'alas Matayim LeBa'alas Maneh Din U'Devarim Ein
Li Imach BeManeh. So basically
Mrs. 200 writes to Mrs. 100 waives her right to dispute her
claim in the first 100. Okay, so it's a special case. Okay,
yeah exactly. So the case is in this first 100, okay, which
is the part that they're all disputing, the second 100 is going
to be divided 50-50, in this first 100, Mrs. 200 says to
Mrs. 100 I'm not going to dispute my claim with you in
this first 100. Of course if she says that you would think
that she should get 66 and two thirds, right? And then it
should be 50 and then it should be 83 and a third.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So אי הכי אימא
סיפא Ei Hachi Eima Seifa של מאתיים ושל שלש מאות שלוש של
זו Shel Matayim VeShel Shelosh Me'os Shalosh Shel Zo so seventy-five seventy-five.
תימא לה אסתלקת נפשך מינה. Teima Lah Istalkat Nafshach Minah.
Okay,
so why doesn't why are they getting 75? She should say to
Mrs. 300 say to Mrs. 200 you gave up your claim here,
right? So how is it that she winds up getting 50,
if you gave up your claim how is it going to be
75 75? Like what's going on and why is it not 66
and two thirds? Okay,
so let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. It says דאמרה
לה D'amrah Lah
מדין ודברים הוא דסליקי נפשאי. MiDin U'Devarim Hu DeSiliki Nafshai.
I only just gave up my claim, I didn't actually give it
to her as a gift. Which means what? So the way רש"י
Rashi explains it means of this 33 and a third, okay, the
reason I am she's getting that is she basically has a claim
against you know competing with two women, right? She's now saying I'm
not going to compete with you, I'm still going to be competing
with her, I'm just not going to make my claim against you.
Okay, so if you're not going to make your claim against her,
you're basically giving her half, right? Because you're competing with these two
women. So she basically manages to get the 50. Alright, but then
still why isn't it
16 and whatever and this is the 80-something or what not, right?
So somehow then it's like no, I conceded her my claim against
her, then what's left now is 100. Now what's
left... no that doesn't work because what's left... no what's left is...
what's left is 50, no 50, what's left is 50 and now
we're going to divide that 50 equally. You got it? So she
basically says, right, I was entitled to 33 and a third, I
conceded my claim to her she walked away with half of my
piece, that was my claim against her, so she walks away with
50. I didn't concede my claim against you and now what's left
in the pot between us is 50. So it's interesting because now
in the 200 case... what? How does the first one get to...
no she gets 75. No, the first the 100 lady... she had
16 and 16, right? I'll drop the fractions.
Everybody is entitled to 33. Right, she was entitled to this because
she was fighting those two people. She conceded her claim
against this woman, she waived her right against this woman, so this
woman got her piece of that, her half of that. Now you
could have said she should walk away with 16 and she should
walk away with the rest, but somehow now she's entitled to go
back to her and claim now I'm going to have my full
claim against you on what remains and what remains is 50 and
we're going to divide that equally in... what do you mean? That's
what תוספות Tosafos says לא פירש שפיר. Lo Peiraish Shapir. Okay, so
it's a very arbitrary context that's being assigned and even within that
context it doesn't make full sense how you would get to that
result. Let's keep on going in the גמרא. Gemara. היו שם, Hayu
sham,
now that we know the real explanation to the משנה, mishnah, it's
even harder to read the גמרא, Gemara, right?
All right. היו שם, Hayu sham, היו שם שלש מאות. Hayu sham
shalosh me'ot.
So the גמרא Gemara says של מאתיים מנה. shel matayim maneh.
So now we're looking at this. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
של מאתיים מנה, shel matayim maneh, שבעים וחמישה הוא דאית לה. shivim
ve-chamisha hu d'it lah.
Why does she get 100? She should have 75. Why should she
have 75? Because let's take a look.
If you go back, I think it's still assuming sort of like
this model that we just set up. So if you go back
to this model we set up where she conceded her claim, so
at stage one you sort of walk away with 50, 25, 25.
That's how you walked away in that stage one. The next 100
is 50, 50, and then the last 100 is not being debated
at all. So that should have led to 50, 75, 175 if
you're maintaining this special context here. Okay, so what did the גמרא
Gemara say? The גמרא Gemara says שבעים וחמישה הוא דאית לה. shivim
ve-chamisha hu d'it lah. She should have gotten 75 if you have
that special way, and if you have the other way it should
have been even something different like whatever, 183 and a third or
something, I don't know. So אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, so שמואל Shmuel
is going to give a different arbitrary explanation to the third one
in order to make it work. בכותבת בעלת שלש מאות לבעלת מאתיים
ולבעלת מנה. Bekotevet ba'alat shalosh me'ot le-ba'alat matayim u-le-ba'alat maneh.
So Mrs. 300 writes to Mrs. 200 and Mrs. 100 and she
says to them, דין ודברים אין לי עמכם במנה, din u-devarim ein
li imachem be-maneh, I am not going to debate the first 100
with you. So this is a different case. So basically Mrs. 300
takes herself out of the picture for the first 100. So the
first 100 gets divided 50, 50. Okay. Now in the next 100,
that is divided equally because she only took herself out of the
picture for the first 100. So she just took herself out. So
that's 50, 50. The next 100 she's back in, 50, 50. The
last 100, that isn't being debated by anybody, so she gets it
all. So that's 50, 100, 150. So basically it's a nice arbitrary
way of saying oh, we just ignore Mrs. 300 in the division
of the first 100 or she took herself out of the picture.
Okay, very arbitrary. Let's take a look. And very unlikely. And very,
well that's also true. If that were our only problem. רבי יעקב
Rabbi Yaakov and so now we have two arbitrary אוקימתות ukimtas of
each line of the משנה Mishnah completely unrelated to one another, right?
So then what type of rule is the משנה mishnah trying to
tell us? רבי יעקב מנהר פקוד משמיה דרבינא אמר, Rabbi Yaakov mi-Nehar
Pekod mishmeih de-Ravina amar, now רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov from נהר פקוד
Nehar Pekod in the name of רבינא Ravina says: רישא בשתי תפיסות
וסיפא בשתי תפיסות. reisha bishtei tefisot ve-seifa bishtei tefisot. No, here's why
it's different. It's because it's not like they all walk into בית
דין Beit Din and בית דין Beit Din says the estate is
100, how are we going to divide this estate? It's actually that
they are seizing the property at different stages. And so when they
actually seize the property it forces us to adjudicate the estate in
different stages because each time they seize the property we have to
figure out what's the judicious division of that seizure. Okay. So let's
take a look. It says רישא בשתי תפיסות וסיפא בשתי תפיסות, reisha
bishtei tefisot ve-seifa bishtei tefisot, דנפלו
שבעים וחמישה בחד זימנא, de-naflu shivim ve-chamisha be-chad zimna, ומאה ועשרים וחמישה
בחד זימנא. u-me'ah ve-esrim ve-chamisha be-chad zimna. Okay, so basically there's also
basically a way of sort of working backwards. He says 50, 75,
75, right? So basically you've got your 100, 200, and 300. And
here's what he says happened. I mean you sort of understand what
he's getting at. He's sort of saying it's sort of like what
Rachel was saying. Oh, well first thing we do is 50, 50,
50, and then we go ahead and we divide the rest. Okay,
that's what you said, right? And I said to you well why
do 50, 50, 50, why not say 40, 40, 40 and then
divide the rest or 60, 60, 60? So he basically says we're
going to say what you just said but we're going to explain
that the circumstances on the ground allowed us to say that. So
he says רישא בשתי
תפיסות דנפלו שבעים וחמישה בחד זימנא. reisha bishtei tefisot de-naflu shivim ve-chamisha
be-chad zimna. Okay,
so 75 first they all got their hands on a piece of
property worth 75. Okay, so they all got their hands on a
piece of property worth 75, what do we do? So we basically,
they all had an equal claim to it so we divided that
75 equally.
Then they all got their hands on a piece of property worth
125, okay? So in that case, now I'm trying to figure out
why this person still gets the claim to the 25.
Hold on.
Somehow this person's claim, because out of that 125, I guess because,
let's
see, trying to remember. Somehow the logic is that she is, oh
because oh yes yes, here's the point. Okay so then now there's
125, it still works with the בבא מציעא Bava Metzia model. Of
this 125, the first 75 of that is still in equal dispute,
right? Right? Because she still says I have 75 of my debt
still to be paid. The first 75 is still of equal dispute.
Since that first 75 is equal dispute, we're going to divide it
like this.
The remaining 50 she walks away, that's in equal dispute between them,
so they're going to divide that like that. Okay, so then it's
50, 50, 50, 75, 75. So it's similar to what Rachel said,
which is oh let's just first divide this and then we'll divide
the rest. But what allows us to do that is we are
going to, because who knows which, how do you chop them up?
Which is the first segment that you divide? So what this is,
the first segment we divide, we'll say it's a case where they
forced us to deal with one segment and then with the next
segment. Okay, so that's how he explains that. In order that to
divide it that exactly. Okay, דנפלו שבעים וחמישה בחד זימנא. denafalu shivim
v'chamisha b'chad zimna. סיפא בשתי תפיסות. seifa b'shtei tefisot.
Now the end is two separate divisions,
this case, an acquisition, well, or grabbing, seizures. דנפלו שבעים וחמישה בחד
זימנא ומאתים ועשרים וחמישה בחד זימנא. denafalu shivim v'chamisha b'chad zimna u-matayim
v'esrim v'chamisha b'chad zimna.
Okay, so here what we had was 75 and 225. So the
first 75 they were in equal dispute: 25, 25, 25, 25, 25.
The next 225, of this, 75 of it was equally disputed because
this Mrs. 100 didn't still have her 75.
Okay, so that gets divided equally. Then we're left with 150. Of
that 150,
she still has a, her claim is still of a full 200.
She got 50. Right? Oh no, no, here's the logic. She's already
staked her claim on 75 and on 75, right? So she's already
staked her claim
on already 150. She's only entitled to stake her claim on a
remaining 50. So okay, so on the 50 that she's entitled to
stake her remaining claim on they divide equally and the last 100
is conceded, so then you get 50, 75, but you have 50.
No, wait, wait, wait, no, no, no, that doesn't work. 150, 25
more,
yeah.
Maybe it's not that
logic. Let me go read רש"י. Rashi.
Wait a
minute,
wait a minute. It's a really hard גמרא Gemara because you have
to try to make it not make sense.
Wait a minute, wait a minute. Conceptually it's similar to what Almon
did in that we're looking for that one number that makes it
all be fighting over simultaneously that would lead to this output. Right,
exactly, but he systemized it. Wait a minute, wait a minute, the
number doesn't work. Well, I just want to point out that we're
talking about fighting, right? Yes, that's right, or seizing property. Wait, wait,
wait. So they have a problem and they have to divide up
something equitably that you know, runs to the same...
No,
but I think that does make a difference.
How so?
Because if you're really fighting, you could have a lot of different
scenarios about what might be right if you're basically saying there's
a third of what we need or a half of what we
need or whatever. Yeah, רש"י, Rashi, רש"י, Rashi, it's
just such a fair point I think, the earliest סוגיא... sugya... Yeah,
רש"י Rashi doesn't explain it. רש"י Rashi just
says, רש"י Rashi doesn't explain it. רש"י Rashi just describes it. He
just says, yeah, when you get to that last 150, somehow the...
what רש"י Rashi says is when you get to this last 150,
you basically take 100 that you divide equally and the 50 you
just give to this one, which is okay, that's nice, but why?
I mean, how do we decide that
the 100 was what we were going to be left, yeah, so
I don't get it. Anyway, but you got the idea. What he's
basically trying to do is figure out how can we stage it
so that the divisions allow this to fall out. Okay, but again,
it's very much of an אוקימתא, okimta, it's not a when this
property was seized in these stages.
So
the last one doesn't need much explanation. The last one just says,
yeah, the half of what you would have gotten. The money that
is here to divide is half of what it would have been.
Wait, what are you saying? The 100 gets half her claim, the
200 gets half her claim? No, yes, of course, what you're saying
is this, is that we just divide it all proportionally? The only
one that doesn't look... require an explanation is the third. Yes, but
the problem is that we have to make it the same model.
Yes, of course this makes sense. This is the model of you
just get your proportionate claim. Yeah, but you can't say that this
is a different model than these. Well we just did. We said—
No, we said it's different circumstances, but it's the same model. If
sometimes you can use this model, why not use this model all
the time? So that's— that is true. That is what's going on—
that is true about the last piece, and that's why it's true
in case of investment, which is the last line of the משנה,
mishna, but you can't just say this follows a different rule. You
can say it follows different— it's talking about different circumstances. Alright, let's
keep on reading. The גמרא gemara says like this.
Okay. תניא זו משנת רבי נתן. Tanya zu mishnat Rabbi Natan. This
משנה mishna is רבי נתן's Rabbi Natan's teaching.
אמר רבי אומר איני רואה דברי רבי נתן באלו, Amar Rabbi omer
eini roeh divrei Rabbi Natan b'elu, which could mean I don't understand
what he's talking about, or it could be I don't agree with
any of this. Okay. אלא חולקים בשוה. Ela cholkim b'shaveh. Okay, now
חולקים בשוה cholkim b'shaveh is what the heck does חולקים בשוה cholkim
b'shaveh mean? Does it mean that you, in this case, you would
basically give a hundred— everybody— you divide the three hundred equally until
everybody's claim is satisfied? So even in this claim, it would be
a hundred, a hundred, a hundred? Okay, that's one way to read
it. תוספות Tosafot says חולקים בשוה cholkim b'shaveh means what we had
assumed based on the בבא מציעא Bava Metzia model, but not Aumann's
version of the בבא מציעא Bava Metzia model, which means, okay, that
in this case it would be you would be חולקים בשוה cholkim
b'shaveh what was sort of left— what was— what wasn't being conceded.
So in the case of two hundred, and you had a hundred,
two hundred, and three hundred, okay, the first hundred is divided equally,
right? So the first hundred is divided equally.
And the next hundred is, this person steps out because she already
staked her claim for that, so then it would be thirty-three, eighty-three,
eighty-three. Okay, and in the case of three hundred,
so the first hundred is this, the second hundred is that, the
third hundred is that, it would be thirty-three, eighty-three, one hundred eighty-three.
Okay, so let's see—
anyway, so he— חולקים בשוה cholkim b'shaveh could just mean you completely
divide it equally until— and until your claim is satisfied and then
you walk away. Or it could mean you follow this בבא מציעא
Bava Metzia model that you concede the part— you concede and what's—
and what you're putting your stake on, that's divided equally. Yes. רבי
Rabbi was the מסדר המשנה. mesader hamishna. Here I have a ברייתא.
braita. רבי Rabbi says in the ברייתא: braita: this משנה mishna is
according to רבי נתן, Rabbi Natan, which is ridiculous. Right. He did
not say that. You said ridiculous. Okay, yeah, I don't agree. Right.
So why— what's the underlying— like why would רבי Rabbi have included
the משנה mishna as the משנה mishna more authoritatively? Right. So you
know that's a really good question because sometimes the גמרא gemara says
like, you know, ראה רבי דבריו של תנא זה ושנאה סתם. ra'ah
Rabbi d'varav shel tanna zeh v'shan'ah stam. Like רבי Rabbi would even
sometimes take a minority opinion, but you know, because like they say
like the person— well, no, but yeah, like they say that the
person who takes the notes in the meeting decides what happened in
the meeting. So רבי, Rabbi, he might— it might be a minority
opinion, but if he's writing the משנה, mishna, he's going to just
present it as the סתם stam and that's his way of backing
that position and giving it more authority. So if you don't agree
with the position, why are you giving it as a סתם? stam?
It's a very good question. You know, I really don't know. I
mean, the language
איני רואה eini roeh might mean that he understands that there's some
system but he doesn't really understand the system, you know, so he's
not really willing to reject it, but nevertheless, why just keep— treat
it סתם? stam? Yeah, I really don't know. Also it says זו
משנת רבי נתן. zu mishnat Rabbi Natan. Is that קב ונקי? kav
v'naki? That's a good point too. Here it says זו משנת רבי
נתן. zu mishnat Rabbi Natan. Right. Was there— were there alternative collections
that— different משניות mishnayot that weren't the סתם? stam? Right. So that
could be that this was a— and— but the other thing I
thought you were talking about is— yeah, that it was part of
a collection but also משנת רבי נתן mishnat Rabbi Natan קב ונקי,
kav v'naki, which means— yeah, so it's— or is that רבי יוסי?
Rabbi Yossi? I don't remember. I don't remember. Okay, now I'm nervous.
Remember. Anyway, so had an alternative collection.
Yeah. Anyway, so if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, right,
תוספות Tosafot says about this question about what בשוה b'shaveh means. First
he thinks it might mean what— you know, every— like hundred, hundred,
hundred. He says פירש רבינו חננאל קיימא לן בהאי הלכתא כרבי. peirash
Rabbeinu Chananel kaima lan b'hai hilchata k'Rabbi.
So first of all, all the brilliance of Robert Aumann is only
for a תורה לשמה Torah lishmah because we don't פוסק posken that
way. We פוסק posken like רבי. Rabbi. Okay. Anyway, ואי אפשר להעמיד
דבריו בזמן שיש שם שלש מאות חולקים בשוה בעלת מנה מנה ובעלת
מאתיים מנה ובעלת שלש מאות מנה, v'ee efshar l'ha'amid d'varav b'zman sheyesh
sham shalosh me'ot cholkim b'shaveh ba'alat maneh maneh u'va'alat matayim maneh u'va'alat
shalosh me'ot maneh, because שמידת הדין לא כן. shemidat hadin lo ken.
Like with this. How is it the woman who has the bigger
claim comes away with no more than any of the other women?
אלא העמידו דברי רבי שמה שחולקים בשוה כל מנה ומנה נוטל בשוה
הלכך חולקין כל עזבון המת בששה חלקים. Ela he'emidu divrei Rabbi shemah
shecholkim b'shaveh kol maneh u'maneh notel b'shaveh hilchach cholkin kol izvon hamet
b'shisha chalakim. That מנה לכל חלק. maneh l'chol chelek. Oh no, I'm
sorry. He doesn't say what I said. Excuse me. Excuse me, I'm
glad that I read this. He doesn't say this, which is the
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia model. What he says חולקים בשוה cholkim b'shaveh
means is the investment model, is the— You get proportional to how
the size of your claim, okay, which is basically you follow this
last one. So if you got
proportional one-sixth of 200 would be what? Let's tell me, 33 and
a third? No, that would be here. One-sixth of 200 is 33
and a third. Oh
right, you're right, yeah, that would be that. So you're right, so
that would be 33 and a third and then it would be
66 and then it would be half, 100. Okay, so that would
be that case. And then the case up here would be 16,
32, and 50. Okay, so that's what תוספות Tosfot says, proportional to
the size of your claim. That's what בשווה b'shaveh means. Yes? So
we follow the last case. All right. Okay, so that's how he
understands רבי, Rebbi, all proportional. And now we finally get to turn
on to the last case: וכן שלושה שהטילו. V'chen shlosha she'hitilu. So
now we're getting to what should seem simpler, okay, which is the
investment model. Everybody gets based on the size of their investment. Great,
makes sense. That's what תוספות Tosfot just said רבי Rebbi is saying,
100, 200, 300, everybody gets the size of their investment.
אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel has to say about this משנה.
Mishna. שניים שהטילו לכיס, Shnayim she'hitilu l'kis, two people put money into
a like a purse, right? They're investing money in some type of
a deal. זה מנה וזה מאתיים, Zeh maneh v'zeh matayim, 100 and
200. So you say one-third and two-thirds. השכר לאמצע. Hasachar l'emtza.
All the money they earn gets divided equally.
Okay, now we're going to see the logic of this, but before
we even get to the logic, I think we should just point
out that this is, yeah well we'll see some implicit agreement. I
think we need to point out that this is an economic disaster,
right? Because who's going to invest money if I'm investing more money,
putting more capital at risk and you're, we're getting an equal division?
Well, it depends who's really like managing the partnership a little bit
more, you might be able to say that. But that's only because
that's a special case when what you're contributing takes place of your
investment, you know, of expertise instead of your investment of money. That's
a special case. Why does he deliberately use two phrases: השכר לאמצע?
Hasachar l'emtza? What does he mean? In because it says what you
mean the language of לאמצע l'emtza as opposed to חולקין בשווה? cholkin
b'shaveh? That's interesting. All right, so let's take a look.
אמר רבא: Amar Rava: מסתברא מילתא דשמואל. Mistavra milta d'Shmuel. So now
we have to try to ring שמואל Shmuel back in. It makes
sense the words of שמואל: Shmuel: בשור לחרישה ועומד לחרישה. b'shor l'charisha
v'omed l'charisha. That what you're dealing with is you're dealing with something
that is a non-divisible asset. We are hiring, we are buying a
cow for an ox for plowing and we're actually going to rent
it out for plowing. So it is true that Michael has more
capital at risk. At the other hand, it's not like his money
is earning X amount while my money is earning Y amount, right?
If we put all that money into a stock and the stock
raised in value, his portions of the stock are
raising proportionally to his investment and mine proportionally mine. Here it's שכר,
sachar, right? Here it's the rental fees that we're earning off of
it, and in a way it's one indivisible asset. So therefore we
can't say two-thirds of the rental fees were due to you. It
was all due to the one indivisible asset of the cow. Okay,
that's at least, even there you would say at the end of
the day he owned two-thirds of the cow but okay, at least
it pulls in שמואל: Shmuel: ועומד לחרישה. v'omed l'charisha. אבל בשור לחרישה
ועומד לטביחה, Aval b'shor l'charisha v'omed l'tveicha, but let's say that they
went ahead and they bought an ox for, now it's a question
about what did they say and what was it used for. They
bought it for plowing but
actually it is slaughtered, okay?
Now רש״י Rashi says עומד לחרישה omed l'charisha is a little funny.
עומד לחרישה Omed l'charisha sounds like it was under- like that the
guy was selling, selling an ox to be slaughtered and they chose
to buy it for plowing. Actually what רש״י Rashi says עומד omed
means is they bought it for plowing but in the end they
decided they could make more money off of slaughtering it and they
slaughtered it. So in the end they turned it into actual something
that is divisible. We sold the meat and you know and actually
so two-thirds of that meat, you know, was yours and one-third of
that meat was mine and therefore that actually is no longer an
indivisible asset and we earn proportionally. So let's just read: זה נוטל
לפי מעותיו וזה נוטל לפי מעותיו. zeh notel l'fi ma'otav v'zeh notel
l'fi ma'otav. Just hold on, I just want to read the opposing
opinion. So that's what he says. So he limits it to a
case of an indivisible asset that's earning sort of money, you know,
not proportional in some non-proportional way. רב המנונא אמר: Rav Hamnuna amar:
אפילו שור לחרישה ועומד לטביחה השכר לאמצע. afilu shor l'charisha v'omed l'tveicha
hasachar l'emtza. No,
as long as they bought it for plowing, that defines their partnership
and therefore even if they wound up slaughtering it, their partnership is
defined in terms of how they bought it as some indivisible asset
divided equally. Now however תוספות Tosfot says, if you take a look
at the little תוספות, Tosfot, תוספות Tosfot says,
where's תוספות? Tosfot?
Yeah,
if you...
which basically alright I sort of extracted that line, but basically he
says if we're buying it to slaughter, then of course we divide
it proportional. So any type of a thing where the assets are
divisible, you know, we're going in and we're, I don't know, we're
buying milk and we're buying fruit and we're, you know, we're transporting
and we're selling it and it's goods and any type of a
thing where the assets are divisible and that was the understanding going
in, everybody agrees it's proportional. Okay, thank God. The only argument is
that we went in initially with an indivisible asset, okay, and then
the debate between שמואל Shmuel and רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna is, we
started with it as an indivisible asset but in the end we
made it divisible. Will that then go by equal or will that
go proportional? But if it started as a divisible asset, then it's
always going to be proportional. Yes, David. In the first case of
the plowing, what is it exactly that's being divided? The profits? Yeah.
But why can't that be divided proportionately? It can,
no no no. So it's not like it's not possible to take
the money and do the math. It's divisible. No, no, no. Yes,
obviously the profit is divisible. It's conceptually the partnership is defined as
a partnership of an ox. You own an ox. So it's not
seen as like I own two-thirds of an ox and I own
one-third of an ox, because, or when the ox is going because
the ox isn't seen as like pieces. The ox is, you know,
an ox that plows only works if it's the whole ox. So
it's basically just more abstracted as we own an ox and the
ox plows and we earn money off the ox. And the money
could be applied in another model? I mean, like you say you
own a boat or you own anything and you see how much
profit you get from the business. And you divide it proportionally. Of
course, proportional is the thing that makes sense, there's no question. שמואל
Shmuel says this weird thing of doing it equally, we have to
try, they might disagree with him, but they're trying to at least
limit him to a case at which it begins to make some
sense out of it. But yeah, it seems it doesn't make, bottom
line is, people aren't going to make investments in that case. Certainly
not going to be the majority investor in those cases. Yes, Joe.
Joe. So the man who was getting married, he gives out כתובה,
ketubah, and he leaves out money for three wives without being possessed,
he don't have nothing, he has
only...
Yeah, but he can make, he can create כתובות ketubahs for any
amount. I mean, he can't do less than 100 for a non-virgin
or less than 200 for a virgin, which is why the smallest
case in the משנה Mishnah was 100, but he can do as
much as you want and even if you don't have the assets
you can create the debt. Maybe when he wrote it he had
the assets. Right, exactly. He died years later. Right, you know what
I mean? If he gets married to three wives, maybe he has
a thousand for each.
Yeah. Alright, or or they they married him because he had a
lot of potential and then he never realized it. Alright, so let's
keep on going.
חברה, Chevre, we have five minutes, we're getting to the משנה, Mishnah,
focus. Alright, it says like this, okay. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you
on this. שנים שהטילו לכיס זה מנה וזה מאתים השכר לאמצע. Shnayim
shehitilu l'kis zeh maneh v'zeh matayim hasachar l'emtza. So you see it
wasn't just שמואל Shmuel that said it, it's a תוספתא, Tosefta, okay?
So מה, mah, and so now we gotta explain the תוספתא. Tosefta.
מאי לאו בשור לחרישה ועמד לטביחה? Mai lav b'shor l'charishah v'omad l'tevichah?
So the גמרא Gemara says, funny why they assumed that case, but
it assumes presumably because if it was a real case that they
went into it just for the meat and it was completely divisible
it would make no sense. But since it's said in an unqualified
way, maybe we have to interpret it as maximally as possible within
some logic. So presumably, it's coming to address the case of buying
it for plowing and in the end slaughtering it, and it still
says you divide it equally. I mean the simple sense is you
always divide it equally, but that would be crazy. So doesn't that
seem to support רבינא? Ravina? So ותיובתא דרבא? utiyuvta d'Rabba? לא בשור
לחרישה ועמד לחרישה. Lo b'shor l'charishah v'omad l'charishah. No, the תוספתא Tosefta
is only when it was only brought for plowing, and that's how
it was used. אבל שור לחרישה ועמד לטביחה מאי? Aval shor l'charishah
v'omad l'tevichah mai? So the גמרא Gemara says what would it be
therefore if it actually was slaughtered? What would you say? זה נוטל
לפי ממו וזה נוטל לפי ממו, Zeh notel l'fi mamo v'zeh notel
l'fi mamo, you'd say proportional. So that's true, אדתני סיפא, ad tanya
seifa, if the end of the תוספתא Tosefta says, לקח זה בשלו
וזה בשלו ונתערבו זה נוטל לפי ממו וזה נוטל לפי ממו. lakach
zeh b'shelo v'zeh b'shelo v'nitarevu zeh notel l'fi mamo v'zeh notel l'fi
mamo. Let's say they had the they had $10,000 that they were
investing, and then one guy took his, you know, his 3,000 and
he bought 10 and he bought, you know, 10 oxen. And this
guy took his 6,000 or whatever and he bought 20 oxen. So
it says in that case, ונתערבו, v'nitarevu,
I lost my place here... wait a minute... I tell you, לקח
זה בשלו וזה בשלו ונתערבו זה נוטל לפי ממו וזה נוטל לפי
ממו. lakach zeh b'shelo v'zeh b'shelo v'nitarevu zeh notel l'fi mamo v'zeh
notel l'fi mamo.
In that case where they actually own different oxen and you just
don't know who's is whose, but you do know that you own
a third and I own two-thirds, then we would divide it, so
that's the only case they imagine dividing it when it actually translated
concretely into different amounts of things, right, into divisible assets. If That's
true, that why that, you know, Rava's position, it should have said
even a less, even a bigger חידוש. chiddush. נפלוג וליתני בדידיה, niflag
v'litni b'dideh,
why not make a distinction even in one ox? במה דברים אמורים?
Bameh devarim amurim? בשור לחרישה ועומד לחרישה. b'shor l'charisha v'omed l'charisha. When
is it? It's equal, when it's all bought and used for plowing.
אבל בשור לחרישה ועומד לטביחה, aval b'shor l'charisha v'omed l'tivicha, but if
it's bought for plowing and then slaughtered, זה נוטל לפי מעותיו וזה
נוטל לפי מעותיו. zeh notel l'fi ma'otav v'zeh notel l'fi ma'otav. You
would divide it equally. So if Rava's right, the תוספתא Tosefta should
have given that case, rather than a case of actually different oxen
and different you know, that discrete objects that got mixed up where
we really do own different oxen. So the גמרא Gemara says הכי
נמי קאמר. hachi nami ka'amar. Where am I? אבל בשור לחרישה ועומד
לטביחה זה נוטל לפי מעותיו וזה נוטל לפי מעותיו. aval b'shor l'charisha
v'omed l'tivicha zeh notel l'fi ma'otav v'zeh notel l'fi ma'otav. הכי נמי
קאמר. Hachi nami ka'amar. That's what it's saying. במה דברים אמורים, Bameh
devarim amurim, when is it equal? בשור לחרישה ועומד לחרישה, b'shor l'charisha
v'omed l'charisha, bought for plowing and used for plowing. אבל בשור לחרישה
ועומד לטביחה, aval b'shor l'charisha v'omed l'tivicha, but if it was bought
for plowing and then it was slaughtered and turned into a divisible
asset, in that case, that would just be just like a classic
case of divisible assets, כמי שקנה זה בשלו וזה בשלו ונתערבו זה
נוטל לפי מעותיו וזה נוטל לפי מעותיו. kemi shekanah zeh b'shelo v'zeh
b'shelo v'nitarvu zeh notel l'fi ma'otav v'zeh notel l'fi ma'otav. Okay? So
anyway you see that Shmuel wasn't saying it in a vacuum, there's
a תוספתא, Tosefta, and the תוספתא Tosefta says, if it's divisible assets
that got mixed up, it's proportional. But it holds out that there
are some cases where it actually is equal. And the question is
what are the cases when it's equal? Only when it remains an
indivisible asset, used for plowing, or even when it got translated into,
or even when it became a divisible asset and got slaughtered. Okay,
but the תוספתא Tosefta is clearly holding out this difference between when
they're divisible assets and non-divisible assets. I understand, I understand. תנן, Tnan,
now we're going to see how it fits in our משנה. Mishnah.
וכן שלשה שהטילו לכיס פיחתו או הותירו כך הן חולקין. v'chen shlosha
shehetilu l'chis pichatu o hotiru kach hen cholkin.
When people invest and the money goes up or goes down, they
divide proportionally. מאי לאו? Mai lav? פיחתו פיחתו ממש הותירו הותירו ממש?
pichatu pichatu mamash hotiru hotiru mamash? Doesn't it mean normal cases of
earning and losing money and you see it's proportional? And then presumably,
now of course you could say, okay, that's a case of divisible
assets, it's not relevant to our discussion, right? That's a natural, a
normal case of investment divisible assets. But somehow the גמרא Gemara wants
to think that maybe the משנה Mishnah is talking about some case
of, some case similar to what we're discussing of non-divisible assets. And
nevertheless it has it being divided equally. How do you explain it?
So the גמרא Gemara says proportionally, excuse me. So the גמרא Gemara
says אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה: amar Rav Nachman amar
Rabbah bar Avuha: לא, לא, לא. lo, lo, lo. That's not what
it means. הותירו, Hotiru, what it means when it says they go
up in value, is זוזא חדתיתי. zuza chadtiti. It means that the
money became new. How does money become new? It's like if you
wore away some of the rust and it became newer and the
actual money itself becomes worth more. Okay. פיחתו Pichatu means אסתירא דצונייתא
astira d'tzunita and פיחתו pichatu means the money became worthless and you
basically wound up using it as like a piece of metal to
put under your heel to put for some type of a health
thing, which means what? It means, I mean it's a little bit
bizarre end of the גמרא. Gemara. You should have said, you know
why it's proportional? Because we're talking about money and we're talking about
a normal case of divisible assets. Okay, but instead it says we
could even be talking about the case where the money itself wasn't
used and it's just the money itself went up or went down
in value. For us it's hard to understand because, you know, we
don't have actual intrinsic value money. But if the money itself goes
up and down in value, so imagine, translate that into our case:
we bought this ox for plowing. If we actually got, you know,
got rental fees from it, according to this, we would divide equally.
But if the cow itself became worth more money and we sold
the cow, or became worth less and we sold it, then when
you're dealing with the actual principal itself, you own two-thirds of the
principal and I own a third, and then it would be proportional.
Yes. Dave says a suggestion that the newer vs old coins may
be that a government had come in and repudiated the old coin.
I see, which actually happened.